<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry>
    <meta>
        <title>Oliphant v. Suquamish Indian Tribe</title>
        <date>1978</date>
        <MainSrc/>
    </meta>
    <body>
        <background>Mark David Oliphant was arrested and charged by tribal police for assaulting a
            tribal police officer in August 1972. Mark Oliphant was a permanent non-Indian resident
            living on the Port Madison Indian Reservation in Washington. Also at the time of
            Oliphant’s arrest, the Suquamish Tribe’s Chief Seattle Days celebration was going on.
            Tribal police knew that this celebration would bring in lots of attention and people so
            the tribe requested additional law enforcement assistance from both the county and the
            Bureau of Indian affairs. Kitsap County ended up sending one deputy and the BIA did not
            send anyone. During the time of Oliphant’s arrest tribal police were the only police
            officers on duty. </background>
        <ruling>
            <div>This resulted in Oliphant applying for a writ of habeas corpus because he was being
                tried under tribal law even though he was a non-Indian. Habeas corpus defends
                individuals from wrongful imprisonment. Habeas corpus orders that a public official
                deliver an imprisoned person to court to prove the reasoning behind their
                imprisonment. </div>
            <div>The lower court rejected Oliphant’s application with the reasoning to keep law and
                order on tribal lands and to maintain tribal sovereignty. </div>
            <div>Oliphant appealed and his case evutallu reached the U.S. Supreme Court. </div>
            <div>The Supreme Court ruled in favor of Oliphant (6-2) stating that tribal courts do
                not have criminal jurisdiction over non-Indians </div>
        </ruling>
        <impact>Tribal courts do not have criminal jurisdiction over non-Indians. This causes a
            complex legal system in order to try perpetrators within violent crime cases. </impact>
    </body>
    <otherLinks>
        <otherSrc/>
    </otherLinks>


</entry>
