<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<newsArticles>
    <entry n="1">
        <meta>
            <artTitle>FEAR NEXT DOOR The man camp connection</artTitle>
            <author>Drew Novak</author>
            <imageCredit>Hope Freier</imageCredit>
            <publisher>Native News Project 2019 | University of Montana</publisher>
            <reservation>Fort Peck Reservation</reservation>
            <source url="https://nativenews.jour.umt.edu/2019/fort-peck/"/>
        </meta>
        <body>
            <p>It was the <fillerTag>North Dakota </fillerTag>license plates that immediately stood
                out to the Thunderchilds. </p>
            <section>
                <p> Sixteen-year-old <fillerTag>Prairiedawn Thunderchild </fillerTag>and her
                    13-year-old younger sister, Tah’nee, were walking to their apartment in northern
                        <fillerTag>Wolf Point </fillerTag>on Aug. 1, 2018. The evening was warm and
                    sticky as they tend to be in the late summer, but the sky was clear as the girls
                    walked past <fillerTag>Southside Elementary </fillerTag>School. </p>
                <p> Then a light blue car containing two men, who the girls would later describe as
                        <qoute person="#">“non-white,”</qoute> slowly sidled up alongside. </p>
                <p> This is not necessarily an odd thing. <fillerTag>Wolf Point </fillerTag>is the
                    largest town in the <reservation><fillerTag>Fort Peck Indian Reservation
                        </fillerTag>in northeast Montana</reservation>. The reservation of mostly
                    Assiniboine and Dakota members covers more than 2 million acres, but
                        <fillerTag>Wolf Point </fillerTag>has a population of approximately 2,700
                    people. And like many small towns with largely <fillerTag>Native American
                    </fillerTag>communities, friends and family bonds are strong. </p>
                <p>
                    <qoute person="#">“My kids know everybody,”</qoute> said their mother,
                    39-year-old Katie Thunderchild, who was in the nearby town of Poplar that
                    evening. “We go to a lot of community things. We know.” </p>
                <p>However, there is a shadow cast over the region, perhaps one that had the sisters
                    hypervigilant, suspicious of anyone, especially with those license plates.</p>
                <p>“When I saw the <fillerTag>North Dakota </fillerTag>plates, it made me think it
                    was ‘mancamp’ or from the oil workers,” <fillerTag>Prairiedawn Thunderchild
                    </fillerTag>said, pronouncing both words of the term mashed into one. “What was
                    going through my mind was they would go and do things to me, or that I would
                    never see my family.” </p>
                <p>Although the men in the car were never caught, the three Thunderchilds are
                    certain of two things: The men in the blue car intended to do the sisters harm,
                    and the North Dakota plates meant the strangers likely came from laborer lodging
                    facilities on nearby oil fields — man camps — in
                        <tempLaborCamps>Williston</tempLaborCamps> and <tempLaborCamps>Watford
                        City</tempLaborCamps>. Both towns are near the site of an oil boom that
                    started in 2006 and peaked in 2012. A perceived increase in violent crime has
                    been present ever since.</p>
                <p>So, the sisters ran. They ran to a nearby park while Tah’nee Thunderchild made
                    the call to local city police, the <fillerTag>Wolf Point Police
                    </fillerTag>Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <qoute person="#">“We had to run,”</qoute> she told dispatch, “because the guys
                    got out and they told us to get in their car. We had to run.”</p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <p>According to the police report, <fillerTag>Officer Tyler Osborne
                    </fillerTag>escorted the girls home, but he was unable to locate the men in the
                    light blue vehicle with the <fillerTag>North Dakota </fillerTag>plates.
                        <fillerTag>Katie Thunderchild </fillerTag>even picked up the search
                    herself.</p>
                <p><qoute person="#">“My mother instinct was, ‘What? Let’s go find it,’”</qoute> she
                    said. “Every blue car that drove by… but we couldn’t find anything.” </p>
                <p><qoute person="#">“You see people around here you’ve never seen before,”</qoute>
                    <fillerTag>Katie Thunderchild </fillerTag>said. “[Man camps] got to be related
                    somehow. The more [oil development] comes about, it’s gonna shake
                    everybody.”</p>
                <p> Laborer lodging facilities have become a necessity for massive energy
                    development projects, which tend to create booms in both economy and population
                    for small, rural towns. They have also become a common core concern in light of
                    the Missing and <fillerTag>Murdered Indigenous Women </fillerTag>crisis, as the
                    cause for much of the victimization of <fillerTag>Native American
                    </fillerTag>women across the country. </p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <p>This idea isn’t entirely ill-founded. According to the <fillerTag>Sovereign
                        Bodies </fillerTag>Institute, there are currently four missing and 12
                    murdered <fillerTag>Native American </fillerTag>women from the Fort
                        <fillerTag>Peck Indian </fillerTag>Reservation, though numbers are almost
                    certainly higher, as many go unreported. A 2019 study from the U.S. Bureau of
                        <fillerTag>Justice Statistics </fillerTag>described a 23 percent increase of
                    violent crime in the Bakken oil region during 2006 to 2012, while regions
                    outside it dropped 8 percent.</p>
                <p> These numbers coincide with the already high rates of violence against Native
                    American women. According to a five-year study released in 2018 by the National
                    Congress of American Indians, 55 percent of <fillerTag>Native American
                    </fillerTag>women have experienced violence from an intimate partner in their
                    lifetime.</p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <p>The picture of man camps many hold is often frightening. Dozens, sometimes
                    hundreds, of men seeking high wages crammed into a tessellation of hastily built
                    shelters, barely supervised and as close to the stereotypical lawless <qoute
                        person="#">“Wild West”</qoute> as it gets. They are seen as hubs for drugs,
                    human trafficking and violence, an image the facility administrators try to
                    avoid.</p>
                <p><qoute person="#">“We don’t even call ourselves a man camp,”</qoute> said E.J.
                    Ross, an office administrator at <tempCamp>Aries Residence Suites</tempCamp>, a
                    lodging facility in <city>Watford, North Dakota</city>. <qoute>“The association
                        with that name conjures up visions that, I don’t care how good of a marketer
                        you are, you say ‘man camps’ people have one mindset.”</qoute></p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <p>As the <fillerTag>Keystone XL </fillerTag>oil pipeline inches ever closer to
                    reality, so does a man camp in Nashua, Montana near the <fillerTag>Fort Peck
                        Indian </fillerTag>Reservation’s southwest border. This stokes fears among
                    the tribal communities that the number of crimes against the tribe’s women will
                    only increase.</p>
                <p><fillerTag>Fort Peck Tribal Executive Board </fillerTag>member <fillerTag>Marva
                        Chapman </fillerTag>underlined these concerns: “The bottom line is a
                    pipeline is contaminating to our water and to our people.”</p>
            </section>
            <p>A study released in 2016 by the <org>Montana Board of Crime Control Statistical
                    Analysis Center</org> and the <org>University of Montana’s Criminology Research
                    Group</org>revealed members of the community felt most unsafe in
                <county/>Roosevelt and <county>Richland</county> counties. More than 75 percent of
                    <county>Roosevelt County</county>lies within <reservation>Fort Peck Indian
                    Reservation </reservation>and contains <fillerTag>Wolf Point </fillerTag>and
                Poplar. Richland holds the town of Sidney, Montana, the home of Sherry Arnold.</p>
            <p>For many non-<fillerTag>Native Americans </fillerTag>outside the <fillerTag>Fort Peck
                </fillerTag>reservation, Arnold’s death provided their first introduction to the
                dark underbelly of oil booms and the influx of outsiders who arrive to take
                advantage of them.</p>
            <p>Arnold was a well-respected high school teacher in Sidney, roughly 50 miles from both
                the <fillerTag>Fort Peck Indian Reservation </fillerTag>and Williston’s own man
                camp. After disappearing in January 2012, her remains were found more than two
                months later near the North Dakota town, an area in the midst of an economic and
                population upswing due to energy development. Arnold’s killer — Colorado’s
                    <fillerTag>Lester Van Waters </fillerTag>Jr. — previously told family and
                friends he was in the region to seek work on the Bakken oil fields.</p>
            <p>Unchecked growth and the outsiders who come with it inflamed a common fear among
                surrounding communities: the oil boom and violent crime were linked.</p>
            <p>“You can go on Facebook, you can go on social media, you can find news reports, and a
                lot of that is personal and anecdotal,” said <fillerTag>Missoula Urban Indian Health
                </fillerTag>Center’s Ivan MacDonald. “You know like, ‘My sister went to a man camp
                to find work and was missing for months.’”</p>
            <p>MacDonald is part of a program focusing on holistic and culturally-based care. He and
                his sister Ivy are also filmmakers working on their first feature-length film
                dedicated to the Missing and <fillerTag>Murdered Indigenous </fillerTag>women
                crisis.</p>
            <p>MacDonald is hardly alone in his mission. <fillerTag>Activist Angeline Cheek
                </fillerTag>is a <fillerTag>Wolf Point </fillerTag> resident and calls the
                reservation home. The 30-year-old is an enrolled Dakota/Lakota tribal member and has
                been a vocal opponent of energy development in and around tribal lands for years,
                citing the trauma such projects can incite, both environmentally and socially. She
                believes there is an unequivocal connection between man camps and missing and
                murdered <fillerTag>Native American </fillerTag>women. Allowing for their
                construction brings far more harm than good, she said. And people need to know about
                it.</p>
            <p><qoute person="#">“You have to know your role,”</qoute> she said. <qoute person="#"
                    >“My role is to educate the people.”</qoute></p>
            <p><fillerTag>The Red Bird Woman Center </fillerTag>in <fillerTag>Wolf Point
                </fillerTag>is also well-versed in dealing with trauma related to sexual and
                physical violence. It is not the easiest place to find. There are no large signs
                covering its nondescript outer walls, no flashy advertisements to draw people in.
                This is by design. The women and children who need this support don’t have to worry
                about their abusers stumbling into its otherwise welcoming doors. This covert
                attitude extends to the center’s employees, who all declined to have their picture
                taken. The risk of visual identification is just too great for the women to feel
                comfortable.</p>
            <p>The center has been in service since the 1980s, providing counseling, shelter, and
                domestic violence, drug and alcohol abuse support. The women who run the center
                believe in the power of awareness and education as oil development springs up around
                    <fillerTag>Native American </fillerTag>communities, bringing with it all too
                familiar burdens.</p>
            <p><qoute person="#">“Indian country wasn’t prepared for such a boom,”</qoute>
                <fillerTag>Crisis Counselor </fillerTag>and <fillerTag>Senior Family </fillerTag>
                Support case manager <fillerTag>Ann Denny </fillerTag>said. “More traffic will bring
                more people who want to spend money and who will put our women and kids in
                danger.”</p>
            <p>Family support case manager <fillerTag>Angela Kennedy </fillerTag>also believes
                higher numbers of outsiders with cash to burn spell trouble.</p>
            <p><qoute person="#">“The people who work in the camps may not be safe people,”</qoute>
                she said. “They make a lot of money fast, and they don’t know what to do with
                it.”</p>
            <p>What they do with it, according to the <fillerTag>Red Bird Woman </fillerTag>Center,
                is funnel it into narcotics, particularly methamphetamine. Young women meet men from
                outside the Indian communities and become addicted to substances, at the mercy of
                those willing to exploit that for sexual purposes, Denny said.</p>
            <p>Violence against women is not the only issue facing reservation residents. There are
                concerns over water quality, drug and human trafficking and the environmental impact
                of adding more and more pipelines to the region. And with those, of course, come
                more man camps.</p>
            <img location="Waterford City N.D." lat="" long="">
                <caption><fillerTag>The Aries Residence Suites </fillerTag>lodging camp in
                        <fillerTag>Waterford City </fillerTag>N.D. is made of dozens of rows of
                    identical buildings, which may have anywhere from one to six beds. In the
                    surrounding hills are the oil fields where most of the residents work during the
                    day.</caption>
            </img>
            <p>Entering the Bakken and <fillerTag>Watford Place </fillerTag>man camps, collectively
                known as Aries <fillerTag>Residence Suites </fillerTag>in Watford City, North
                Dakota, the first thing you notice is the mud. It’s a rusty orange slop peppered
                with equally rusty orange pebbles. It coats the roads that weave through the rows of
                identical mobile home-like structures and sticks to everything. It’s spattered up
                the sides of tenants’ cars, their boots, the modest landings in each doorway.</p>
            <p><fillerTag>Aries Residence Suites </fillerTag>can house 300 residents. The camp is
                located near North Dakota’s western border and about an hour and a half drive east
                from the limits of the <fillerTag>Fort Peck </fillerTag>reservation.</p>
            <p>The camp is surprisingly mute during the day. Laborers leave their rentals empty as
                they work in nearby old fields. As evening approaches, most head straight to their
                accommodations. A few stop by the main office briefly to pick up mail. A man, both
                his arms covered in tattoos, haggles with site supervisor E.J. Ross over rental
                pricing.</p>
            <p><fillerTag>The Bakken </fillerTag>oil boom affected <fillerTag>Watford City
                </fillerTag>hard, with a population that soared from 1,744 in 2010 to 6,523 only
                seven years later. More than tripling in size puts a strain on any city, and men
                drawn by the promise of hard-earned oil money need places to stay. That’s where
                companies like Aries come in, providing support for a housing infrastructure that
                just couldn’t handle such explosive growth.</p>
            <p>Though painstaking efforts are taken to distance themselves from the <qoute
                    person="#">“man camp”</qoute> label — these are <qoute person="#">“residence
                    lodges,”</qoute> as Ross said — it is true areas like these are built mainly to
                take care of men working the nearby oil fields. But women and children are not
                forbidden from staying at Bakken Suites, said camp manager Jeni Belman. Belman lives
                in a private unit herself, as many Aries employees do.</p>
            <p>Aries contains temporary housing that can cost as little as $25 per night for the
                four-occupancy <qoute person="#">“dormitory style”</qoute> units with shared kitchen
                and living space. Those looking for something more private can even stay in <qoute
                    person="#">“executive suites,”</qoute> fully-private cabins with kitchen
                appliances costing $45 a night if staying for more than a month. With housekeeping
                and all utilities included in the price (and internet and T.V. to boot), it’s no
                wonder these arrangements have a widespread appeal.</p>
            <p><fillerTag>Aries Residence Suites </fillerTag>might be ritzier than any image the
                term <qoute person="#">“man camp”</qoute> might engender — stereotypical magnets for
                criminals of all sorts, void of good intentions — but Ross believes there is some
                truth to the hype.</p>
            <p>Background checks are more <qoute person="#">“unofficial”</qoute> than exhaustive,
                sometimes involving little more than a Facebook screening. Alcohol is allowed
                on-site, though guns are only relegated to tenants’ vehicles. Ross has personally
                had to step in on occasions men become <qoute person="#">“a little too
                    fixated”</qoute> on female residents. And people are notoriously
                unpredictable.</p>
            <p><qoute person="#">“You never know who you’re going to meet,”</qoute> he said. “You
                don’t know what’s on their mind.”</p>
            <p><fillerTag>Eastern Montana </fillerTag>and western North Dakota’s isolation and
                    <qoute person="#">“badlands”</qoute> locale can also be attributed to an element
                of danger. It’s the sort of place drivers need to keep a close eye on their gas
                tanks; the next pump could be miles away. Something is bound to happen occasionally
                in a space that vast, Ross said. He recalls <qoute person="#">“six or seven”</qoute>
                instances of missing women cases in the last year.</p>
            <p><qoute person="#">“This is a state where people disappear,”</qoute> Ross said.</p>
            <p><fillerTag>Lieutenant Brian Erwin </fillerTag>of the <fillerTag>Wolf Point Police
                    Department </fillerTag>isn’t so sure increased violent crime rates can be blamed
                entirely on oil development and man camps. Drugs, alcohol and the violence that
                accompanies such things have been issues on reservations for decades, he said.</p>
            <p><qoute person="#">“We don’t have to look for some crazy new reason when we know what
                    goes on,”</qoute> said Erwin, who has worked with the police department since
                2000. “Why do the women who live here get victimized every damn day?
                    <fillerTag>Native American </fillerTag>women are abused and neglected here on a
                daily basis from the earliest ages.” </p>
            <p><fillerTag>Fort Peck </fillerTag>tribal police <fillerTag>Captain James Summers
                </fillerTag>is also reluctant to put too much focus on the introduction of man camps
                to the region. Summers has been a member of the tribal police for 27 years, and
                chief for five. He cuts an imposing figure, quiet-voiced but direct, even seated
                behind his desk at the Bureau of <fillerTag>Indian Affairs </fillerTag> building in
                Poplar, 22 miles east of Wolf Point.</p>
            <p>Summers believes the Bakken oil boom is responsible for an explosion of narcotics,
                especially opioids, more than anything.</p>
            <p><qoute person="#">“It’s tough to say that domestic violence is influenced by the
                    Bakken,”</qoute> Summers said. “It’s always been a problem here. Whether or not
                it’s influenced by the Bakken, I don’t know.”</p>
            <p>But according to Angeline Cheek, the rates of missing and murdered indigenous women
                have reached crisis levels. Cheek was inspired to create a <qoute person="#"
                    >“community action plan,”</qoute> a set of guidelines for local townships to
                address the problems that Native Americans face. It contains points like the need
                for a more responsive police force in cases of missing persons and human
                trafficking, of course, but also increased cultural education so youths <qoute
                    person="#">“know how to behave as a Dakota.”</qoute></p>
            <p>There is a section dedicated to teaching youths about trafficking and how they can
                protect themselves. Another asks for more intensive trauma training for those
                directly involved in such cases. Cheek’s main goal is to educate, a role she says
                she was born to do. As the Nashua camp seems likelier each day, it’s more important
                than ever for community members to brace for the future, Cheek said.</p>
            <p>“Our ancestors used to prepare for harsh winters to come, gathering berries and
                drying meat,” she said. <qoute person="#">“Today we have to keep our children safe,
                    our elders.”</qoute></p>
            <p>Indeed, the <fillerTag>Fort Peck Tribal Executive Board </fillerTag>does seem to be
                coming around to the concept. As of the council meeting on March 28, the leaders say
                they hope to implement an action plan similar to Cheek’s for speedier responses in
                the near future.</p>
            <p>For the Thunderchilds, life goes on, even if the family is shaken by the experience.
                    <fillerTag>Katie Thunderchild </fillerTag>has since doubled-down on her <qoute
                    person="#">“mothering instinct,”</qoute> fearing for her daughters anytime they
                are left alone. Each day, local news highlights a missing woman, man or child, she
                said. What should she think if her daughters haven’t checked in within 20 minutes?
                An hour? With man camps so near, Thunderchild’s mind jumps to the worst.</p>
            <p>Prairiedawn and Tah’nee are all smiles now, beaming while they show off traditional
                regalia they have sewn themselves hanging from their bedroom walls. They debate with
                their mother about what to get for dessert at McDonald’s. A vanilla milkshake? No,
                no. Strawberry.</p>
            <p>But the events of that August evening stick like that rusty <fillerTag>North Dakota
                </fillerTag>mud. Worry turns to panic swiftly these days when the girls haven’t made
                recent contact, a feeling increasingly shared by others in the family.</p>
            <p><qoute person="#">“My grandmother’s like that,”</qoute> Thunderchild said. “She’s
                always been like that, but now it’s more.”</p>
            <p>So mom never lets them go anywhere, Tah’nee Thunderchild said with an understanding
                sigh. At least, not without following the rules. There are boundaries to where the
                sisters can walk alone. They must carry a cell phone at all times.</p>
            <p><qoute person="#">“We used to go for walks and nobody would bother us or anything
                    until that day,”</qoute>
                <fillerTag>Prairiedawn Thunderchild </fillerTag>said. But now, <qoute person="#">“we
                    watch out for men.”</qoute></p>
        </body>



    </entry>

</newsArticles>
