<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<entry>
    <meta>
        <artTitle>Why Aren’t Fossil Fuel Companies Held Accountable for Missing and Murdered
            Indigenous Women?</artTitle>
        <author>ABAKI BECK</author>
        <imageCredit>Sarah Morris/Getty Images</imageCredit>
        <publisher pubdate="OCT 5, 2019">YES! Magazine</publisher>
        <reservation>N/A</reservation>
        <source
            url="https://www.yesmagazine.org/environment/2019/10/05/native-fossil-fuel-missing-murdered-indigenous-women-mmiwg"
        />
    </meta>
    <p>Later this month, the <fillerTag>South Dakota Water Management Board </fillerTag>will be
        holding five hearings on water permits needed for the <fillerTag>Keystone XL
        </fillerTag>pipeline expansion, which will cross several rivers as it makes its way from the
        tar sands in Alberta to Steele City, Nebraska. If the pipeline expansion is approved—it’s
        been on hold for nearly a decade —it will affect several tribal and <fillerTag>First Nations
        </fillerTag>communities along its route. Tribal activists fear this will bring not only
        economic and environmental impacts, but also sexual violence.</p>

    <p>Angeline Cheek, a community advocate on the <fillerTag>Fort Peck Reservation </fillerTag>in
        Northeastern Montana, is vehemently opposed to the extension. As proposed,
            <fillerTag>Keystone XL </fillerTag>would cross just a few miles from the western side of
        the reservation. On the eastern side, across the <fillerTag>North Dakota </fillerTag>
        border, are the Bakken oil fields.</p>

    <p>Cheek’s organization provides workshops and information to reservation residents on the
        dangers of man camps in the Bakken area. Man camps are large company-owned housing units
        that people who come to work in the oil fields can move into.</p>

    <p>With the Bakken oil boom, these man camps have increased in the region. Population growth
        because of an extractive industry leads to a surge of individuals—mostly men—who are paid
        well and living temporarily in rural areas they aren’t otherwise connected to. Since the
        boom, violent crime, sex trafficking, and rape cases have increased, according to tribal
        police and local activists.</p>

    <p>Cheek and a group of advocates—whose motto is “no fear”—have also created a safety plan with
        input from the community in anticipation of these impacts. Part of the proposed plan is a
        text- and call-based early warning system to alert community members of missing people;
        AMBER alert is only for children.</p>

    <p>Though the group has received support from some tribal programs and the broader community,
        tribal leadership has not signed onto the community safety plan. “I have relatives here who
        I don’t want to go missing,” Cheek said. “The tribe needs to start thinking ahead. …The
        tribe should be doing the work I’m doing. They should be thinking of preventative ways to
        keep the community safe.”</p>

    <p>National attention turned to the Bakken in 2012, when Sherry Arnold, a White teacher, was
        raped and murdered by two men who came to the Bakken in search of work. Yet many Native
        victims don’t receive this kind of support, Cheek said. “When something happens to an
        Indigenous person, to a Native person, why isn’t that being heard? We’re just another
        number.”</p>

    <p><fillerTag>The Sovereign Bodies </fillerTag>Institute’s <fillerTag>MMIW Database
        </fillerTag>—the only comprehensive, up-to-date database tracking missing and murdered
        Indigenous women in the U.S. and Canada—details 529 cases of missing and murdered Indigenous
        women in Montana, North Dakota, South Dakota, and Nebraska, the states which
            <fillerTag>Keystone XL </fillerTag>will traverse. Nearly 80% of these cases are unsolved
        or no perpetrators have been found, and 30% are active missing persons cases. One of those
        women is <fillerTag>Olivia Lone </fillerTag>Bear, whose body was found nine months after she
        went missing from the Fort <fillerTag>Berthold Reservation </fillerTag>in the heart of the
        Bakken in October 2017. Some fear these numbers will increase if more man camps come to the
            <fillerTag>Great Plains </fillerTag>region.</p>

    <p><fillerTag>The Canadian </fillerTag>government has begun to recognize the connection between
        the extractive industry and violence against Native women. <fillerTag>In June </fillerTag>of
        this year, Canada’s <fillerTag>National Inquiry </fillerTag>into Missing and
            <fillerTag>Murdered Indigenous Women </fillerTag>and Girls released a 1,200-page report
        concluding three years of community hearings, story gathering, and forensic research. The
        report showed a strong link between extraction zones on the missing and murdered women
        crisis in Canada. It specifically cited rotational shift work, sexual harassment in the
        workplace, substance abuse, economic insecurity, and a largely transient workforce as
        contributing to increased violence against Native women in communities near fossil fuel
        infrastructure.</p>

    <p>Also, as an <fillerTag>Amnesty International </fillerTag>report notes, transient workers are
        often not counted in census numbers, leading to overwhelmed public services. According to
        the report, in British Columbia, “frontline service providers supporting marginalized
        individuals, such as women’s shelters and food banks, describe a situation of constant
        crisis, as needs outpace their capacity to respond.”</p>


    <p>A sign referring to missing Native women and the establishment of ‘man camps’ in fracking and
        oil drilling sections of the <fillerTag>United States </fillerTag>hangs in the Plaza in
        Santa Fe, New Mexico, during the 2019 Women’s March. Photo by Robert Alexander/Getty
        Images.</p>

    <p>What’s worse, in the U.S., tribal communities often don’t have jurisdiction to respond to the
        increase in crimes. <fillerTag>The Major Crimes Act </fillerTag>of 1885 largely limited what
        crimes tribal courts can prosecute, and Oliphant vs. Suquamish in 1978 asserted that tribal
        courts cannot prosecute non-Native offenders, even those who live on tribal lands. When the
        Violence <fillerTag>Against Women Act </fillerTag>was last reauthorized in 2013, it expanded
        tribal jurisdiction to include some cases related to domestic violence, dating violence, and
        violation of protection orders. But it didn’t expand tribal jurisdiction to include sex
        trafficking or many other forms of sexual violence.</p>

    <p>“One of the immediate fixes we’re pushing for is reauthorization of VAWA,” said Annita
        Lucchesi, executive director of the <fillerTag>Sovereign Bodies </fillerTag>Institute. The
        new version of the law would expand tribal jurisdiction to cover sexual violence, sex
        trafficking and stalking, among other changes.</p>

    <p>In areas where tribes don’t have jurisdiction, either FBI or county sheriffs are supposed to
        provide support, depending on the state. But that doesn’t always happen. “What we’re seeing
        is that county sheriffs in [some] states and FBI in other areas are understaffed and
        underfunded,” Lucchesi says. This has real impacts. According to a <fillerTag>Government
            Accountability </fillerTag> Office report, federal prosecutors between 2005 and 2009
        declined to prosecute 67% of the 2,500 cases in <fillerTag>Indian Country
        </fillerTag>involving sexual violence that were referred to them.</p>

    <p>If tribes can’t hold individuals accountable for violence, what about the companies
        themselves? “I think companies have a responsibility to ensure that they’re holding their
        workers to a high standard of conduct on and off the job, especially if they’re living in
        company housing like man camps,” Lucchesi said. “And I think that they have a responsibility
        for public safety.”</p>

    <p>Cheek agrees, and also thinks that the Department of Justice and local law enforcement can do
        more to protect their communities, including sharing data on crime. “They have the research,
        how come they aren’t letting the reservation know? How come they aren’t working with the
        reservations to develop safety plans?”</p>

    <p><fillerTag>Though Native </fillerTag>activists and communities often recognize and call out
        the connection between violence in their communities and the intrusion of extractive
        industries, mainstream environmental justice movements and gender-based violence initiatives
        often don’t overlap. As expansion of oil pipelines continues—like <fillerTag>Keystone XL
        </fillerTag>and <fillerTag>Trans Mountain </fillerTag>in Canada—activists remain vigilant
        about their impacts on the communities around them.</p>

    <p>Resource extraction impacts more than just the economy and the environment. It can endanger
        the lives of Native women, as communities in Canada and <fillerTag>North Dakota
        </fillerTag>have already experienced. “It creates this culture of using and abuse,” Lucchesi
        says. “If you can use and abuse the water and land, you can use and abuse the people around
        you too.”</p>
</entry>
