<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<entry>
    <meta>
        <artTitle>CLOSE TO HOME Overlapping jurisdiciton leave families in the dark</artTitle>
        <author>Rebecca Keith</author>
        <imageCredit>Winter Ramos</imageCredit>
        <publisher>Native News Project 2019 | University of Montana</publisher>
        <reservation>Rocky Boy's Reservation</reservation>
        <source url="https://nativenews.jour.umt.edu/2019/fort-peck/"/>
    </meta>
    <p>In the early hours of <date when="2018">July 7, 2018</date>, Tasha New Breast-Morrow lay
        awake on her living room couch. Red and blue flashes lit up the darkness outside her house.
        She lived close to Box Elder, on Rocky Boy’s Indian Reservation.</p>

    <p>She had last seen her best friend, Shannon Licht-Morsette, a couple hours earlier.
        Licht-Morsette was sitting on the wooden steps across the street in front of her
        single-story yellow house, waiting for her 14-year-old son to return home on a bus from
        South Dakota.</p>

    <p><q ref="#">“I know that night when it happened, this whole block, I swear it was pitch
            black,”</q> she said. There were no street lights or porch lights like normal. <q
                ref="#">“I had to use a flashlight to walk outside.”</q></p>

    <p>An hour later, she started getting messages from her friends that something happened to
        Licht-Morsette. The street was blocked off by police cars and an ambulance. Licht-Morsette’s
        mom, Marla Boe Morsette, stood by her truck with her grandsons, sobbing.</p>

    <p>New Breast-Morrow woke up throughout the night and each time she heard her friend’s mother
        screaming and crying.</p>

    <p>Shannon Licht-Morsette had been murdered.</p>

    <p>Licht-Morsette was found dead by her 14-year-old son and his uncle around 1 a.m. Tribal
        police showed up first. They called the FBI and the Hill County Coroner’s office, who showed
        up around 2:30 a.m. and examined the body together.</p>

    <p>Within hours of her death, Licht-Morsette’s murder investigation involved three different law
        enforcement agencies: the FBI, Hill County Sheriff’s department and the Rocky Boy Police
        Department. This is normal for major crimes committed on the reservation. The number of
        agencies often involved in these crimes can make it difficult for a victim’s family and
        friends to know where to get information.</p>

    <p>In 2018, the Seattle-based Urban Indian Health Institute released a report on Missing and
        Murdered Indigenous Women and Girls. The report found that jurisdiction issues often lead to
        misreported numbers as many women are completely overlooked and their tribal nation is often
        left in the dark.</p>

    <p>“Tribal nations must have the ability to advocate for their citizens living in urban areas
        when they go missing or are killed,” the report states. <q ref="#">“This is a courtesy
            extended to all other sovereign nations … the nation is notified of their death and
            [they are] able to advocate for their citizen’s case and family.”</q></p>

    <p>New Breast-Morrow and Licht-Morsette lived directly across the street from each other. Both
        single moms, they had two sons close in age who watched cartoons together while their
        mothers cooked dinner and listened to old-school rap.</p>

    <p>New Breast-Morrow shook her head in disbelief. <q ref="#">“She was the kindest
            person.”</q> Licht-Morsette would have given her last dollar away. </p>

    <p>She would spend a lot of nights sleeping on New-Breast Morrow’s couch in their living room
        with her youngest son. One time, Licht-Morsette put a lighter to her mouth to a light a
        cigarette, but forgot to put the cigarette in her mouth and accidentally burned herself.</p>

    <p><q ref="#">“She was really goofy, like Silly Sally,”</q> New Breast-Morrow said.</p>

    <p>New Breast-Morrow sits on that couch now, her hands crossed tightly in her lap, a rose tattoo
        on each thumb and pink tipped dark hair in a ponytail. Her 5-year-old son empties a
        cardboard box of Hot Wheels cars on to her green, glass coffee table. He holds one up and
        talks to her.</p>

    <p><q ref="#">“I swear her and her youngest son had their own language. They would talk to
            each other,”</q> New Breast-Morrow recounts with a laugh because she never could
        understand what the two were saying. </p>

    <p>Later that Saturday, around 11 a.m., the FBI questioned New Breast-Morrow with the tribal
        police present.</p>

    <p>New Breast-Morrow said in a Facebook message that she remembers the FBI leading the
        questioning and the tribal police observing and mostly listening</p>

    <p>The day after, the same tribal police officers came back without the FBI, and asked more
        questions. This time they surrounded her house, placed her and her children on the couch in
        the living room and did a search.</p>

    <p>According to New Breast-Morrow, an officer told her he drove by her house everyday and saw
        the accused murderer standing on her porch. New Breast-Morrow told him that wasn’t true and
        that she never saw police driving by her house. She said he tried to make it seem like she
        was lying.</p>

    <p>According to an article published by the Great Falls Tribune on <date when="2018">July 10,
            2018</date>, Tribal Police Chief Larry Bernard said that he didn’t know many details
        about the case and that he had been told to turn the case over to the FBI. </p>

    <p>New Breast-Morrow heard nothing for several months. She kept her blinds closed and lived in
        constant paranoia. Finally in October, she heard about an arrest on Facebook and felt some
        relief.</p>

    <p>Under the Major Crimes Act of 1885, the FBI has the jurisdiction to investigate major crimes
        on tribal reservations: murder, manslaughter, rape, assault with intent to kill, arson,
        burglary, and larceny. The list has since been updated to include more crimes such as felony
        assault, sexual abuse and kidnapping.</p>

    <p>This often leaves tribal authorities on the sidelines, watching as outside forces dictate how
        to investigate crimes that target their own citizens, neighbors and family.</p>

    <p><q person="#">“It’s got a lot to do with communication, talking openly and not being
            territorial,”</q> said Harlan Baker, tribal council chairman for the <res>Rocky Boy’s Indian
        Reservation</res>, where Licht-Morsette lived. He said the relationship between the three agencies
        is not terrible, but it could be much better. It could also get much worse as soon as
        someone new is in charge of any of the agencies.</p>

    <p>The FBI has 35 field agents covering several areas in Montana. The chairman said his tribe
        has tried to establish a better relationship with the FBI, but they rarely come to the
        tribal council meetings.</p>

    <p><q person="#">“We invite the FBI to come and sit with us, and they come and sit maybe once
            every couple years,” </q>Chairman Baker said. Since he began serving on the council in
        2008, the longest an agent has stayed in the region was about three years. It seems every
        year there is a new agent responsible for cases on Rocky Boy’s.</p>

    <p>He believes the tribe needs their help more often than the FBI gives, because the tribal law
        enforcement does not have training to handle more serious cases like abduction and murder,
        and the tribal courts have limits on the severity of sentences they can give. The department
        also lacks communication with state law enforcement. They’ve rarely worked together, even
        though cases often cross borders into state jurisdiction.</p>

    <p>Chairman Baker thinks that written protocols for multiple jurisdictions collaborating on
        cases would be important so the agencies consistently work together.</p>

    <p>The council has considered measures to allow more severe sentences in tribal courts, but have
        yet to actually propose tribal legislation governing communication with other law
        enforcement agencies.</p>

    <p>In Licht-Morsette’s case, the tribal police believed that the murderer was hiding in
        New-Breast Morrow’s house, but they gave no indication during the FBI interview that they
        suspected she was hiding him. The FBI only questioned New Breast-Morrow about the people who
        were over at Licht-Morsette’s house, the night she died.</p>

    <p>Licht-Morsette’s eldest son was coming back to his mom’s house after being gone for a month.
        According to the affidavit, he texted her around 12:20 a.m. on <date when="2018">July 7,
            2018</date>. Forty minutes later, he walked into their house and found his mother lying
        on the floor in her bedroom. There were red scratches on her neck and a bite mark in her
        left arm. Shattered picture frames lay around her legs. His 1-year-old brother was in the
        house with her.</p>

    <p>Her son was friends with another teenager in the village, Elena Garcia’s son. Garcia’s ex,
        Brandon Sutherland, was staying with her that weekend, along with his brother Gavin
        Sutherland, Adam Swan, and Lynnell Boldt. Garcia lived a couple blocks down from
        Licht-Morsette.</p>

    <p>With all of them staying at her house, she couldn’t stand being around the four of them and
        left early in the day, Garcia said. She said they were all acting strange, and saying weird
        things, especially Gavin Sutherland.</p>

    <p>“I don’t know if it was because he stayed awake too long and he started to see stuff and hear
        stuff. But I think maybe that’s why he was kinda going crazy,” Garcia said. It made her
        nervous. </p>

    <p>Garcia was just getting to be good friends with Licht-Morsette.</p>

    <p><q person="#">“She was always nice even though me and her weren’t that close, we would always
            come down and borrow coffee and whatever,” </q>Garcia said. When the two finally both
        had coffee, missing sugar would send them back to each others’ houses. </p>

    <p>The Sutherland brothers, Swan and Boldt, went over to Licht-Morsette’s house to hang out that
        day. The last time Garcia saw her, she said she wished the people in her house would leave
        because her son was coming home.</p>

    <p><q person="#">“She was so nice to everyone, she was too nice to tell them people to
            leave,”</q> Garcia said.</p>

    <p>Garcia found out about Licht-Morsette’s death on Facebook. That’s how most news of missing
        and murdered Native American women is spread.</p>

    <p>Native American women go missing at far higher rates than any other race in Montana.
        According to the Department of Justice, Native American women make up more than 30 percent
        of female missing persons reports filed in Montana in the last three years. Native Americans
        make up just under 7 percent of the population of Montana. Most of them don’t live on
        reservations, falling under state jurisdiction.</p>

    <p>Data from the department confirms what Native American communities have been saying for
        decades, their women are being targeted. But this number does not grasp the true scope of
        the problem.</p>

    <p>Data from the Sovereign Bodies Institute puts the number of Native American women still
        missing in Montana in the past three years at 35. The Department of Justice puts the number
        at 15. The institute, run by Native Americans, gathers data from law enforcement, but also
        by aggregating information from Facebook pages and on-the-ground reporting with families.
        The institute puts the total number of unresolved cases in Montana at 66 in the last three
        years.</p>

    <p>In its 2018 report, the Urban Indian Health Institute used both official Freedom of
        Information Act Requests and grassroots reporting to compile data of missing and murdered
        Native American women. The report found 153 cases of missing and murdered Native American
        women nationwide that were not in law enforcement data bases. Great Falls had five cases
        that are not located in law enforcement records, which is the 10th highest rate of any city
        in the country.</p>

    <p>Billings was ranked second, with 17 cases.</p>

    <p>“Some cities still do not have systems that are searchable by race or include American
        Indian, Native American as categories,” the report states, calling for cities to update
        their record keeping tactics. <q person="#">“No agency can adequately respond to violence it
            does not track.”</q></p>

    <p>The difference between data from the Sovereign Bodies Institute and the Department of
        Justice’s data, further shows the confusion between Native American tribes in Montana and
        the law enforcement agencies responsible for recovering their loved ones. At least 20 Native
        American girls have gone missing in Montana in the last three years without ever being
        recorded by responding law enforcement agencies.</p>

    <p><q person="#"><q ref="#"><q ref="#">“We wish for quicker responses,”</q></q></q> Baker said.</p>

    <p>Baker hasn’t heard anything about Licht-Morsette’s case from the FBI since they came to the
        reservation to investigate the night of the murder. He heard about the murder charges being
        filed from a local TV news station.</p>

    <p>When he was younger, he remembers hearing about the prejudice and racism in the FBI. He’d
        hear people say that the federal agencies didn’t want to come onto the reservation.</p>

    <p><q person="#">“If they don’t want to work with us, is it still that kind of mentality?
            Possibly.”</q> Baker said. “Their actions speak louder than their words so if they don’t
        wanna work with us there is something going on besides the lack of communication.”</p>

    <p>In December 2018, the Congressional Committee on Indian Affairs held a hearing on the problem
        of missing and murdered women in Indian Country. Montana Senator John Tester invited several
        Native Americans with missing family members to speak in front of the committee.</p>

    <p>They detailed a lack of response and communication from state and federal agencies alike. And
        even when the agencies did track down a suspect, the evidence was too sparse to
        prosecute.</p>

    <p>Representatives from the BIA, the FBI, and the Office of Investigative and Forensic Sciences
        at the National Institute for Justice were present to testify. They described their
        procedures when dealing with crimes in Indian Country, but all the families who had
        firsthand experience with the agencies testified that what they said at the hearing and what
        they did on the ground did not match.</p>

    <p><q person="#"><q ref="#"><q ref="#">“This is your failure,”</q></q></q> said Heidi Heitkamp, a former senator from North
        Dakota. “When you don’t have prosecution, you have no deterrents and it’s open season on
        people who live in Indian Country.”</p>

    <p>It took the FBI several months to put together evidence to arrest a suspect in
        Licht-Morsette’s murder. Even then, the suspect was arrested in Washington on unrelated
        charges and confessed to the murder when questioned by FBI agent David Brown.</p>

    <p>According to the affidavit written by Agent Brown, the evening Litch-Morsette was murdered,
        she had guests she wished would leave and she confronted Gavin Sutherland about some money
        of hers that was suddenly missing. She and Sutherland went into her room. Then she
        screamed.</p>

    <p><q person="#"><q ref="#"><q ref="#">“It was the sound a woman makes when she gets hit … or when she’s scared,”</q></q></q>
        Boldt said in the affidavit.</p>

    <p>According to the affidavit, Sutherland confessed to hearing voices and seeing a shadow while
        he was talking to Licht-Morsette, and they told him to kill her, so he strangled her.</p>

    <p>He was arrested on Oct. 10, 2018, and charged with second degree murder and is currently in
        the custody of U.S. Marshals. Sutherland pleaded not guilty to one count of second degree
        murder and a jury trial is scheduled for <date when="2019">May 13, 2019</date>.</p>

    <p>Licht-Morsette’s neighborhood is at the western edge of the reservation. Snow on the distant
        Bear’s Paw Mountains has melted in ribbons. Spots of evergreen and aspen trees dot the
        mountains.</p>

    <p>At the very end of the road, next to New Breast-Morrow’s and across from Licht-Morsette’s, is
        Leno Jo Henderson’s house. The three of them were the closest of friends. The Henderson’s
        have an old wedding arch made of aspen wood over their steps. Their two horses, one black
        and one palomino, fuzzy from the winter, live in the field next to them.</p>

    <p>Henderson stands in front of New Breast-Morrow’s open door in pajama pants, holding a fuzzy
        white cat with brown spots.</p>

    <p>Henderson is tall, with her dark hair pulled back in a half ponytail and smile lines on her
        face. In her soft voice she talks about how they just finished up a month long stretch of
        below freezing weather, so they’re all going a little stir crazy. Her husband helped all the
        houses on the street with fire wood. They had to burn the wood they had set aside for a
        barn.</p>

    <p>Two of their cats run across the street and behind Licht-Morsette’s house, which is still
        empty.</p>

    <p>She said it took a long time for the housing authority to come out and put plywood over the
        front door. Their littlest kids kept going inside the house looking for Aunt Shanni.</p>

    <p>Henderson wishes they would find someone to rent the house to already. <q person="#">“Get rid
            of the darkness inside,”</q> she said. </p>
</entry>
