<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="article.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<entry>
    <meta>
        <artTitle>Why Aren’t Fossil Fuel Companies Held Accountable for Missing and Murdered
            Indigenous Women?</artTitle>
        <author>ABAKI BECK</author>
        <imageCredit>Sarah Morris/Getty Images</imageCredit>
        <publisher pubdate="OCT 5, 2019">YES! Magazine</publisher>
        <reservation>N/A</reservation>
        <source
            url="https://www.yesmagazine.org/environment/2019/10/05/native-fossil-fuel-missing-murdered-indigenous-women-mmiwg"
        />
    </meta>
    <p>Later this month, the <org>South Dakota Water Management Board </org>will be holding five
        hearings on water permits needed for the <org>Keystone XL </org>pipeline expansion, which
        will cross several rivers as it makes its way from the tar sands in Alberta to <city>Steele
            City, Nebraska</city>. If the pipeline expansion is approved—it’s been on hold for
        nearly a decade —it will affect several tribal and First Nations communities along its
        route. Tribal activists fear this will bring not only economic and environmental impacts,
        but also sexual violence.</p>
    <p><person>Angeline Cheek</person>, a community advocate on the <res>Fort Peck Reservation
        </res>in <state>Northeastern Montana</state>, is vehemently opposed to the extension. As
        proposed, <org>Keystone XL </org>would cross just a few miles from the western side of the
        reservation. On the eastern side, across the <state>North Dakota </state> border, are the
        Bakken oil fields.</p>
    <p>Cheek’s organization provides workshops and information to reservation residents on the
        dangers of man camps in the Bakken area. Man camps are large company-owned housing units
        that people who come to work in the oil fields can move into.</p>
    <p>With the Bakken oil boom, these man camps have increased in the region. Population growth
        because of an extractive industry leads to a surge of individuals—mostly men—who are paid
        well and living temporarily in rural areas they aren’t otherwise connected to. Since the
        boom, violent crime, sex trafficking, and rape cases have increased, according to tribal
        police and local activists.</p>
    <p>Cheek and a group of advocates—whose motto is “no fear”—have also created a safety plan with
        input from the community in anticipation of these impacts. Part of the proposed plan is a
        text- and call-based early warning system to alert community members of missing people;
        AMBER alert is only for children.</p>
    <p>Though the group has received support from some tribal programs and the broader community,
        tribal leadership has not signed onto the community safety plan. “I have relatives here who
        I don’t want to go missing,” Cheek said. “The tribe needs to start thinking ahead. …The
        tribe should be doing the work I’m doing. They should be thinking of preventative ways to
        keep the community safe.”</p>
    <p>National attention turned to the Bakken in 2012, when Sherry Arnold, a White teacher, was
        raped and murdered by two men who came to the Bakken in search of work. Yet many Native
        victims don’t receive this kind of support, Cheek said. “When something happens to an
        Indigenous person, to a Native person, why isn’t that being heard? We’re just another
        number.”</p>
    <p><org>The Sovereign Bodies Institute’s MMIW Database </org>—the only comprehensive, up-to-date
        database tracking missing and murdered Indigenous women in the U.S. and Canada—details 529
        cases of missing and murdered Indigenous women in Montana, North Dakota, South Dakota, and
        Nebraska, the states which <org>Keystone XL </org>will traverse. Nearly 80% of these cases
        are unsolved or no perpetrators have been found, and 30% are active missing persons cases.
        One of those women is <person>Olivia Lone Bear</person>, whose body was found nine months
        after she went missing from the <res>Fort Berthold Reservation</res> in the heart of the
        Bakken in October 2017. Some fear these numbers will increase if more man camps come to the
        Great Plains region.</p>
    <p><org>The Canadian government</org> has begun to recognize the connection between the
        extractive industry and violence against Native women. In June of this year,
            <report>Canada’s National Inquiry into Missing and Murdered Indigenous Women and Girls
        </report>released a 1,200-page report concluding three years of community hearings, story
        gathering, and forensic research. The report showed a strong link between extraction zones
        on the missing and murdered women crisis in Canada. It specifically cited rotational shift
        work, sexual harassment in the workplace, substance abuse, economic insecurity, and a
        largely transient workforce as contributing to increased violence against Native women in
        communities near fossil fuel infrastructure.</p>
    <p>Also, as an <org>Amnesty International </org>report notes, transient workers are often not
        counted in census numbers, leading to overwhelmed public services. According to the report,
        in British Columbia, “frontline service providers supporting marginalized individuals, such
        as women’s shelters and food banks, describe a situation of constant crisis, as needs
        outpace their capacity to respond.”</p>
    <p>A sign referring to missing Native women and the establishment of ‘man camps’ in fracking and
        oil drilling sections of the United States hangs in the Plaza in Santa Fe, New Mexico,
        during the 2019 Women’s March. </p>
    <img>
        <caption>Photo by Robert Alexander/Getty Images</caption>
    </img>
    <p>What’s worse, in the U.S., tribal communities often don’t have jurisdiction to respond to the
        increase in crimes. <report>The Major Crimes Act of 1885</report> largely limited what
        crimes tribal courts can prosecute, and Oliphant vs. Suquamish in 1978 asserted that tribal
        courts cannot prosecute non-Native offenders, even those who live on tribal lands. When the
            <report>Violence Against Women Act</report> was last reauthorized in 2013, it expanded
        tribal jurisdiction to include some cases related to domestic violence, dating violence, and
        violation of protection orders. But it didn’t expand tribal jurisdiction to include sex
        trafficking or many other forms of sexual violence.</p>
    <p>“One of the immediate fixes we’re pushing for is reauthorization of VAWA,” said
            <person>Annita Lucchesi</person>, executive director of the <org>Sovereign Bodies
            Institute</org>. The new version of the law would expand tribal jurisdiction to cover
        sexual violence, sex trafficking and stalking, among other changes.</p>
    <p>In areas where tribes don’t have jurisdiction, either <org>FBI</org> or county sheriffs are
        supposed to provide support, depending on the state. But that doesn’t always happen. <q
            ref="#">“What we’re seeing is that county sheriffs in [some] states and FBI in other
            areas are understaffed and underfunded,”</q><person> Lucchesi</person> says. This has
        real impacts. According to a <org>Government Accountability Office</org> report, federal
        prosecutors between 2005 and 2009 declined to prosecute 67% of the 2,500 cases in Indian
        Country involving sexual violence that were referred to them.</p>
    <p>If tribes can’t hold individuals accountable for violence, what about the companies
        themselves? <q ref="#">“I think companies have a responsibility to ensure that they’re
            holding their workers to a high standard of conduct on and off the job, especially if
            they’re living in company housing like man camps,”</q>
        <person>Lucchesi</person> said. <q ref="#">“And I think that they have a responsibility for
            public safety.”</q></p>
    <p><person>Cheek</person> agrees, and also thinks that the <org>Department of Justice</org> and
        local law enforcement can do more to protect their communities, including sharing data on
        crime. <q ref="#">“They have the research, how come they aren’t letting the reservation
            know? How come they aren’t working with the reservations to develop safety
        plans?”</q></p>
    <p>Though Native activists and communities often recognize and call out the connection between
        violence in their communities and the intrusion of extractive industries, mainstream
        environmental justice movements and gender-based violence initiatives often don’t overlap.
        As expansion of oil pipelines continues—like <org>Keystone XL </org>and <org>Trans Mountain
        </org>in Canada—activists remain vigilant about their impacts on the communities around
        them.</p>
    <p>Resource extraction impacts more than just the economy and the environment. It can endanger
        the lives of Native women, as communities in Canada and <state>North Dakota </state>have
        already experienced. <q ref="#">“It creates this culture of using and abuse,”</q>
        <person>Lucchesi</person> says. <q ref="#">“If you can use and abuse the water and land, you
            can use and abuse the people around you too.”</q></p>
</entry>
