<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../articles/article.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<entry dateID="2016-03-14">
    <meta>
        <title>Inside the Temporary Homes of North Dakota Oil Workers</title>
        <author>JORDAN G. TEICHER</author>
        <imageCredit>Kyle Cassidy</imageCredit>
        <publisher>The Slate Group</publisher>
        <pubDate>2016-03-14</pubDate>
        <source
            url="https://slate.com/culture/2016/03/kyle-cassidy-photographs-the-homes-of-oil-workers-in-north-dakota-in-the-bakken-goes-boom.html"
        />
    </meta>
    <body>
        <section>
            <p>Making an oil boom is about more than just figuring out how to get the black stuff
                out of the ground. It also requires establishing services and facilities—including,
                first and foremost, housing—for an influx of workers staying for an unpredictable
                amount of time. </p>
            <p>The task has been a tall one in Western North Dakota, where thousands of oil workers
                and, sometimes, their families, have flocked in the years since technological
                advances made possible the extraction of oil from a reserve called the Bakken
                Formation. A new collection of studies on this great migration, The Bakken Goes
                Boom: Oil and the Changing Geographies of Western North Dakota, which was edited by
                William Caraher and Kyle Conway, is available from the Digital Press at the
                University of North Dakota as a free download. It can also be purchased in print. </p>

            <p>Photographing oil workers had never crossed Kyle Cassidy’s mind, but when the Digital
                Press asked him to contribute imagery for the book, he traveled nearly 2,000 miles
                from Philadelphia in February 2013 to investigate the housing situation in the
                region. He’s visited two more times since and plans to go again. </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <p>Tioga, North Dakota. Hess refinery in the background. Hess and its predecessor
                Amerada Petroleum have been in the Bakken since the beginning.</p>
            <p>Copyright Kyle Cassidy</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <p>Scott Collins, camp in Watford City, North Dakota. “They told me I needed to have
                some money in my pocketbook because it’s going to be high-priced, if you can even
                find a place. Just to park this mobile home is $700. To rent a house, $3,000 a
                month. That’s cheap. I had to get a roll of duct tape when I got up here for my
                sewer. $13. The local businesses here gouge people.” </p>
            <p>Copyright Kyle Cassidy</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <p>Keith Day. Camp near Alexander, North Dakota. “When I got here, I hitchhiked up here,
                I didn’t have nothing but a bag on my back. I stayed at a church. There’s only one
                church over there that will let you sleep there, in Williston. I stayed there about
                three or four days, and then I found a room for rent for $100 a week.”</p>
            <p>Copyright Kyle Cassidy</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <p>While homes, apartment complexes, and other permanent residences have been built to
                house workers, the accommodations Cassidy photographed were temporary, including
                RVs, tents, and “man camps,” or energy company–built barracks. </p>

            <p>“One thing that North Dakota is definitely not interested in is a bunch of ghost
                towns and abandoned equipment rusting in fields, so in many cases what you’re
                allowed to do in terms of building is highly regulated,” Cassidy said via email. </p>

            <p>Today, a drop in oil prices has slowed production, which means there aren’t enough
                workers in the state to fill all the available real estate. But at the height of the
                boom, the region struggled to make room for the flood of new arrivals. Cassidy found
                the challenge most memorably encapsulated in the story of Gregg Thompson, an artist
                from Washington who moved to Williston, North Dakota, in 2012 and, unable to find an
                open apartment or a hotel room, briefly lived in a dumpster—an experience he
                recorded for his YouTube channel, where he goes by Gregg Zart—before moving into an
                RV.</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <p>Double room at Capital Lodge, near Tioga, North Dakota. This camp closed down in
                2015.</p>
            <p>Copyright Kyle Cassidy</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <p>Samantha, Wheelock, North Dakota. “The boom has brought good and bad. For everybody
                here it’s brought good and bad. For jobs, I mean, I work at a convenience store and
                make a very, very nice salary to manage the store. It’s been a very good thing for
                me. For a lot of people coming here they’re finding what they’re looking for.”</p>
            <p>Copyright Kyle Cassidy</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <p>Gregg Zart left the Pacific Northwest looking for work in the oil patch. He spent his
                first few days in Williston living in a dumpster and later became a YouTube
                celebrity with his updates about life in the Bakken.</p>
            <p>Copyright Kyle Cassidy</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <p>Wheelock, North Dakota. Families from Utah moved to the Bakken to work in the oil
                industry.</p>
            <p>Copyright Kyle Cassidy</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <p>Living in rough conditions in an isolated environment made for tight, if fleeting,
                communities. But since none of the workers were able to predict how long the boom
                would last, Cassidy said, most didn’t bother getting too invested in their lodgings.
                As a result, a lot of them didn’t look especially lived-in, particularly the
                barracks, which were, according to Cassidy, “almost clinically barren.” Indeed, home
                in North Dakota, for some of the workers Cassidy interviewed, was simply a place to
                catch a few precious hours of sleep before another long and grueling day in the
                field.</p>

            <p>“There were some people who were practically monastic—they worked, they slept, they
                sent money home.”</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <p>Tioga, North Dakota. Waiting for work outside a series of portable housing units.
                Even at the height of the boom, work, particularly in trucking, could be
                irregular.</p>
            <p>Copyright Kyle Cassidy</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <p>Larry, camp in Watford City, North Dakota. “This kind of lifestyle is just nothing
                new to us. But we are at an age now where our kids are all gone … so, why not come
                out here for a while and make some real money?” </p>
            <p>Copyright Kyle Cassidy</p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <p>Valeria. Coffee stand at the entrance to a camp near Tioga, North Dakota. “I was only
                supposed to be here for a week or two. Since I didn’t have a plan, I thought I’d
                look around for a job. But all the jobs around were like 12 hours a day, six days a
                week. And I couldn’t do that with my son.”</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</entry>
