<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<newsArticles>
    <entry n="1">
        <meta>
            <artTitle>FEAR NEXT DOOR The man camp connection</artTitle>
            <author>Drew Novak</author>
            <publisher>Native News Project 2019 | University of Montana</publisher>
            <source url="https://nativenews.jour.umt.edu/2019/fort-peck/"/>
        </meta>
        <body>
            <p>It was the North Dakota license plates that immediately stood out to the
                Thunderchilds. </p>
            <p> Sixteen-year-old Prairiedawn Thunderchild and her 13-year-old younger sister,
                Tah’nee, were walking to their apartment in northern Wolf Point on Aug. 1, 2018. The
                evening was warm and sticky as they tend to be in the late summer, but the sky was
                clear as the girls walked past Southside Elementary School. </p>
            <p> Then a light blue car containing two men, who the girls would later describe as
                “non-white,” slowly sidled up alongside. </p>
            <p> This is not necessarily an odd thing. Wolf Point is the largest town in the Fort
                Peck Indian Reservation in northeast Montana. The reservation of mostly Assiniboine
                and Dakota members covers more than 2 million acres, but Wolf Point has a population
                of approximately 2,700 people. And like many small towns with largely Native
                American communities, friends and family bonds are strong. </p>
            <p> “My kids know everybody,” said their mother, 39-year-old Katie Thunderchild, who was
                in the nearby town of Poplar that evening. “We go to a lot of community things. We
                know.” </p>
            <p>However, there is a shadow cast over the region, perhaps one that had the sisters
                hypervigilant, suspicious of anyone, especially with those license plates.</p>
            <p>“When I saw the North Dakota plates, it made me think it was ‘mancamp’ or from the
                oil workers,” Prairiedawn Thunderchild said, pronouncing both words of the term
                mashed into one. “What was going through my mind was they would go and do things to
                me, or that I would never see my family.” </p>
            <p>Although the men in the car were never caught, the three Thunderchilds are certain of
                two things: The men in the blue car intended to do the sisters harm, and the North
                Dakota plates meant the strangers likely came from laborer lodging facilities on
                nearby oil fields — man camps — in Williston and Watford City. Both towns are near
                the site of an oil boom that started in 2006 and peaked in 2012. A perceived
                increase in violent crime has been present ever since.</p>
            <p>So, the sisters ran. They ran to a nearby park while Tah’nee Thunderchild made the
                call to local city police, the Wolf Point Police Department.</p>
            <p> “We had to run,” she told dispatch, “because the guys got out and they told us to
                get in their car. We had to run.”</p>
            <p>According to the police report, Officer Tyler Osborne escorted the girls home, but he
                was unable to locate the men in the light blue vehicle with the North Dakota plates.
                Katie Thunderchild even picked up the search herself.</p>
            <p>“My mother instinct was, ‘What? Let’s go find it,’” she said. “Every blue car that
                drove by… but we couldn’t find anything.” </p>
            <p>“You see people around here you’ve never seen before,” Katie Thunderchild said. “[Man
                camps] got to be related somehow. The more [oil development] comes about, it’s gonna
                shake everybody.”</p>
            <p> Laborer lodging facilities have become a necessity for massive energy development
                projects, which tend to create booms in both economy and population for small, rural
                towns. They have also become a common core concern in light of the Missing and
                Murdered Indigenous Women crisis, as the cause for much of the victimization of
                Native American women across the country. </p>
            <p>This idea isn’t entirely ill-founded. According to the Sovereign Bodies Institute,
                there are currently four missing and 12 murdered Native American women from the Fort
                Peck Indian Reservation, though numbers are almost certainly higher, as many go
                unreported. A 2019 study from the U.S. Bureau of Justice Statistics described a 23
                percent increase of violent crime in the Bakken oil region during 2006 to 2012,
                while regions outside it dropped 8 percent.</p>
            <p> These numbers coincide with the already high rates of violence against Native
                American women. According to a five-year study released in 2018 by the National
                Congress of American Indians, 55 percent of Native American women have experienced
                violence from an intimate partner in their lifetime.</p>
            <p>The picture of man camps many hold is often frightening. Dozens, sometimes hundreds,
                of men seeking high wages crammed into a tessellation of hastily built shelters,
                barely supervised and as close to the stereotypical lawless “Wild West” as it gets.
                They are seen as hubs for drugs, human trafficking and violence, an image the
                facility administrators try to avoid.</p>
            <p>“We don’t even call ourselves a man camp,” said E.J. Ross, an office administrator at
                Aries Residence Suites, a lodging facility in Watford, North Dakota. “The
                association with that name conjures up visions that, I don’t care how good of a
                marketer you are, you say ‘man camps’ people have one mindset.”</p>
            <p>As the Keystone XL oil pipeline inches ever closer to reality, so does a man camp in
                Nashua, Montana near the Fort Peck Indian Reservation’s southwest border. This
                stokes fears among the tribal communities that the number of crimes against the
                tribe’s women will only increase.</p>
            <p>Fort Peck Tribal Executive Board member Marva Chapman underlined these concerns: “The
                bottom line is a pipeline is contaminating to our water and to our people.”</p>
            <p>A study released in 2016 by the Montana Board of Crime Control Statistical Analysis
                Center and the University of Montana’s Criminology Research Group revealed members
                of the community felt most unsafe in Roosevelt and Richland counties. More than 75
                percent of Roosevelt County lies within Fort Peck Indian Reservation and contains
                Wolf Point and Poplar. Richland holds the town of Sidney, Montana, the home of
                Sherry Arnold.</p>
            <p>For many non-Native Americans outside the Fort Peck reservation, Arnold’s death
                provided their first introduction to the dark underbelly of oil booms and the influx
                of outsiders who arrive to take advantage of them.</p>
            <p>Arnold was a well-respected high school teacher in Sidney, roughly 50 miles from both
                the Fort Peck Indian Reservation and Williston’s own man camp. After disappearing in
                January 2012, her remains were found more than two months later near the North
                Dakota town, an area in the midst of an economic and population upswing due to
                energy development. Arnold’s killer — Colorado’s Lester Van Waters Jr. — previously
                told family and friends he was in the region to seek work on the Bakken oil
                fields.</p>
            <p>Unchecked growth and the outsiders who come with it inflamed a common fear among
                surrounding communities: the oil boom and violent crime were linked.</p>
            <p>“You can go on Facebook, you can go on social media, you can find news reports, and a
                lot of that is personal and anecdotal,” said Missoula Urban Indian Health Center’s
                Ivan MacDonald. “You know like, ‘My sister went to a man camp to find work and was
                missing for months.’”</p>
            <p>MacDonald is part of a program focusing on holistic and culturally-based care. He and
                his sister Ivy are also filmmakers working on their first feature-length film
                dedicated to the Missing and Murdered Indigenous women crisis.</p>
            <p>MacDonald is hardly alone in his mission. Activist Angeline Cheek is a Wolf Point
                resident and calls the reservation home. The 30-year-old is an enrolled
                Dakota/Lakota tribal member and has been a vocal opponent of energy development in
                and around tribal lands for years, citing the trauma such projects can incite, both
                environmentally and socially. She believes there is an unequivocal connection
                between man camps and missing and murdered Native American women. Allowing for their
                construction brings far more harm than good, she said. And people need to know about
                it.</p>
            <p>“You have to know your role,” she said. “My role is to educate the people.”</p>
            <p>The Red Bird Woman Center in Wolf Point is also well-versed in dealing with trauma
                related to sexual and physical violence. It is not the easiest place to find. There
                are no large signs covering its nondescript outer walls, no flashy advertisements to
                draw people in. This is by design. The women and children who need this support
                don’t have to worry about their abusers stumbling into its otherwise welcoming
                doors. This covert attitude extends to the center’s employees, who all declined to
                have their picture taken. The risk of visual identification is just too great for
                the women to feel comfortable.</p>
            <p>The center has been in service since the 1980s, providing counseling, shelter, and
                domestic violence, drug and alcohol abuse support. The women who run the center
                believe in the power of awareness and education as oil development springs up around
                Native American communities, bringing with it all too familiar burdens.</p>
            <p>“Indian country wasn’t prepared for such a boom,” Crisis Counselor and Senior Family
                Support case manager Ann Denny said. “More traffic will bring more people who want
                to spend money and who will put our women and kids in danger.”</p>
            <p>Family support case manager Angela Kennedy also believes higher numbers of outsiders
                with cash to burn spell trouble.</p>
            <p>“The people who work in the camps may not be safe people,” she said. “They make a lot
                of money fast, and they don’t know what to do with it.”</p>
            <p>What they do with it, according to the Red Bird Woman Center, is funnel it into
                narcotics, particularly methamphetamine. Young women meet men from outside the
                Indian communities and become addicted to substances, at the mercy of those willing
                to exploit that for sexual purposes, Denny said.</p>
            <p>Violence against women is not the only issue facing reservation residents. There are
                concerns over water quality, drug and human trafficking and the environmental impact
                of adding more and more pipelines to the region. And with those, of course, come
                more man camps.</p>
            <img location="Waterford City N.D." lat="" long="">
                <caption>The Aries Residence Suites lodging camp in Waterford City N.D. is made of
                    dozens of rows of identical buildings, which may have anywhere from one to six
                    beds. In the surrounding hills are the oil fields where most of the residents
                    work during the day.</caption>
            </img>
            <p>Entering the Bakken and Watford Place man camps, collectively known as Aries
                Residence Suites in Watford City, North Dakota, the first thing you notice is the
                mud. It’s a rusty orange slop peppered with equally rusty orange pebbles. It coats
                the roads that weave through the rows of identical mobile home-like structures and
                sticks to everything. It’s spattered up the sides of tenants’ cars, their boots, the
                modest landings in each doorway.</p>
            <p>Aries Residence Suites can house 300 residents. The camp is located near North
                Dakota’s western border and about an hour and a half drive east from the limits of
                the Fort Peck reservation.</p>
            <p>The camp is surprisingly mute during the day. Laborers leave their rentals empty as
                they work in nearby old fields. As evening approaches, most head straight to their
                accommodations. A few stop by the main office briefly to pick up mail. A man, both
                his arms covered in tattoos, haggles with site supervisor E.J. Ross over rental
                pricing.</p>
            <p>The Bakken oil boom affected Watford City hard, with a population that soared from
                1,744 in 2010 to 6,523 only seven years later. More than tripling in size puts a
                strain on any city, and men drawn by the promise of hard-earned oil money need
                places to stay. That’s where companies like Aries come in, providing support for a
                housing infrastructure that just couldn’t handle such explosive growth.</p>
            <p>Though painstaking efforts are taken to distance themselves from the “man camp” label
                — these are “residence lodges,” as Ross said — it is true areas like these are built
                mainly to take care of men working the nearby oil fields. But women and children are
                not forbidden from staying at Bakken Suites, said camp manager Jeni Belman. Belman
                lives in a private unit herself, as many Aries employees do.</p>
            <p>Aries contains temporary housing that can cost as little as $25 per night for the
                four-occupancy “dormitory style” units with shared kitchen and living space. Those
                looking for something more private can even stay in “executive suites,”
                fully-private cabins with kitchen appliances costing $45 a night if staying for more
                than a month. With housekeeping and all utilities included in the price (and
                internet and T.V. to boot), it’s no wonder these arrangements have a widespread
                appeal.</p>
            <p>Aries Residence Suites might be ritzier than any image the term “man camp” might
                engender — stereotypical magnets for criminals of all sorts, void of good intentions
                — but Ross believes there is some truth to the hype.</p>
            <p>Background checks are more “unofficial” than exhaustive, sometimes involving little
                more than a Facebook screening. Alcohol is allowed on-site, though guns are only
                relegated to tenants’ vehicles. Ross has personally had to step in on occasions men
                become “a little too fixated” on female residents. And people are notoriously
                unpredictable.</p>
            <p>“You never know who you’re going to meet,” he said. “You don’t know what’s on their
                mind.”</p>
            <p>Eastern Montana and western North Dakota’s isolation and “badlands” locale can also
                be attributed to an element of danger. It’s the sort of place drivers need to keep a
                close eye on their gas tanks; the next pump could be miles away. Something is bound
                to happen occasionally in a space that vast, Ross said. He recalls “six or seven”
                instances of missing women cases in the last year.</p>
            <p>“This is a state where people disappear,” Ross said.</p>
            <p>Lieutenant Brian Erwin of the Wolf Point Police Department isn’t so sure increased
                violent crime rates can be blamed entirely on oil development and man camps. Drugs,
                alcohol and the violence that accompanies such things have been issues on
                reservations for decades, he said.</p>
            <p>“We don’t have to look for some crazy new reason when we know what goes on,” said
                Erwin, who has worked with the police department since 2000. “Why do the women who
                live here get victimized every damn day? Native American women are abused and
                neglected here on a daily basis from the earliest ages.” </p>
            <p>Fort Peck tribal police Captain James Summers is also reluctant to put too much focus
                on the introduction of man camps to the region. Summers has been a member of the
                tribal police for 27 years, and chief for five. He cuts an imposing figure,
                quiet-voiced but direct, even seated behind his desk at the Bureau of Indian Affairs
                building in Poplar, 22 miles east of Wolf Point.</p>
            <p>Summers believes the Bakken oil boom is responsible for an explosion of narcotics,
                especially opioids, more than anything.</p>
            <p>“It’s tough to say that domestic violence is influenced by the Bakken,” Summers said.
                “It’s always been a problem here. Whether or not it’s influenced by the Bakken, I
                don’t know.”</p>
            <p>But according to Angeline Cheek, the rates of missing and murdered indigenous women
                have reached crisis levels. Cheek was inspired to create a “community action plan,”
                a set of guidelines for local townships to address the problems that Native
                Americans face. It contains points like the need for a more responsive police force
                in cases of missing persons and human trafficking, of course, but also increased
                cultural education so youths “know how to behave as a Dakota.”</p>
            <p>There is a section dedicated to teaching youths about trafficking and how they can
                protect themselves. Another asks for more intensive trauma training for those
                directly involved in such cases. Cheek’s main goal is to educate, a role she says
                she was born to do. As the Nashua camp seems likelier each day, it’s more important
                than ever for community members to brace for the future, Cheek said.</p>
            <p>“Our ancestors used to prepare for harsh winters to come, gathering berries and
                drying meat,” she said. “Today we have to keep our children safe, our elders.”</p>
            <p>Indeed, the Fort Peck Tribal Executive Board does seem to be coming around to the
                concept. As of the council meeting on March 28, the leaders say they hope to
                implement an action plan similar to Cheek’s for speedier responses in the near
                future.</p>
            <p>For the Thunderchilds, life goes on, even if the family is shaken by the experience.
                Katie Thunderchild has since doubled-down on her “mothering instinct,” fearing for
                her daughters anytime they are left alone. Each day, local news highlights a missing
                woman, man or child, she said. What should she think if her daughters haven’t
                checked in within 20 minutes? An hour? With man camps so near, Thunderchild’s mind
                jumps to the worst.</p>
            <p>Prairiedawn and Tah’nee are all smiles now, beaming while they show off traditional
                regalia they have sewn themselves hanging from their bedroom walls. They debate with
                their mother about what to get for dessert at McDonald’s. A vanilla milkshake? No,
                no. Strawberry.</p>
            <p>But the events of that August evening stick like that rusty North Dakota mud. Worry
                turns to panic swiftly these days when the girls haven’t made recent contact, a
                feeling increasingly shared by others in the family.</p>
            <p>“My grandmother’s like that,” Thunderchild said. “She’s always been like that, but
                now it’s more.”</p>
            <p>So mom never lets them go anywhere, Tah’nee Thunderchild said with an understanding
                sigh. At least, not without following the rules. There are boundaries to where the
                sisters can walk alone. They must carry a cell phone at all times.</p>
            <p>“We used to go for walks and nobody would bother us or anything until that day,”
                Prairiedawn Thunderchild said. But now, “we watch out for men.”</p>
        </body>



    </entry>

</newsArticles>
